Guide to the William Benton Papers 1839-1973
University of Chicago Library
Benton, William. Papers
1839-1973
384 linear feet (613 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
William Benton (1900-1973) was an advertising executive, publisher, university administrator, U.S. senator and diplomat. Contains personal and professional correspondence, reports, legal documents, account books, diaries, manuscripts, speeches, research notes, transcripts of radio and television broadcasts, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, photographs, awards, and mementos. Papers highlight Benton's business and investment successes as well as his contributions to education and public affairs. Includes material relating to Encyclopaedia Britannica (1941-1973); Encyclopaedia Britannica Films (1939-1973); America First Committee; the Committee for Economic Development (1942-1973); Muzak (1941-1973); Benton & Bowles (1925-1973); the U.S. State Department (1941-1973); UNESCO (1946-1973); the McCarthy era; the establishment of Voice of America; the University of Chicago Board of Trustees; the Benton Foundation (1958-1973) commitments to Brandeis University, the University of Bridgeport, the University of Connecticut, the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, the Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, and the American Shakespeare Festival; and Connecticut and national politics (1948-1973).
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
A dynamic man of broad interests and innovative flair, William Burnett Benton achieved distinction in many fields during his seventy-three years. He was blessed with a nearly unerring talent for the marketplace, but he is remembered especially for broad-ranging contributions in education and public affairs.
Born in Minneapolis on April 1, 1900, Benton was the first child of Charles William Benton, a Congregationalist clergyman and University of Minnesota professor, and Elma Hixson Benton, a country school superintendent. Benton and his younger brother, Daniel Hixson, grew up in a close-knit family which prized its activist heritage; their paternal grandparents had been missionaries in Lebanon from the 1840s through the 1870s, and the Hixsons were prominent in Democratic reform politics in Minnesota. Particularly through the forceful example of his mother, Benton early was imbued with humanitarian and public service ideals which his later life exemplified.
When Benton was thirteen his father died, and the family's situation changed radically. Young William entered Shattuck Academy in Faribault, Minnesota, on a partial scholarship, spending most vacations helping his mother in an ill-fated Montana homesteading venture undertaken with her father and brother. Though Benton disliked the isolated summers and the military regimen of the academic year, he was buoyed by the prospect of following a long line of Yale-educated Bentons who had been ministers, teachers, and professionals. Each year he stood close to the top of his class, but he always found time for extracurricular activities. In addition to sports, he supplemented his meager funds as Shattuck's sole agent for memory books, class pins, stationery, and a binder he invented for the new school paper. Through his schoolboy enterprise he began to discover entrepreneurial and selling talents which were to alter the direction of his ambitions.
In June 1917 Benton confidently took his final exams at Shattuck and the entrance exams for Yale. The college's English and mathematics requirements presented no difficulty, but he was shocked when he failed the French and Latin exams. Suddenly his dreams seemed unattainable, forcing the high school graduate to reevaluate the future.
In the meantime Elma Benton, seeking to improve her long-range career possibilities in teaching, had decided to earn a master's degree in education at Columbia University's Teachers College. Her solution to her elder son's predicament was to enroll him at Carleton College, where his aunt, Dr. Mary Benton, was dean of women. To his surprise Benton found all aspects of Carleton life congenial, and he weighed the notion of going against his mother's wishes by finishing his undergraduate work there. The dilemma disappeared when Congress passed a draft law covering ages 18 to 45, for Benton immediately left for Yale, where he was inducted into the Student Army Training Corps. Benton's hopes for military service were dashed only two months later with the signing of the armistice.
He stayed at Yale to retake the entrance examinations and in 1918 entered as a sophomore. Although quickly recognized as a prize debater and a frequent contributor to the Yale Record, it was a trying year for Benton academically and socially. He felt his Midwestern background and schooling branded him an outsider, and he resented the handicap as he adjusted to the social and intellectual atmosphere of the eastern institution. In early 1919 Benton began to make decisions which pointed him toward a business career. First came involvement in a college-calendar franchise, by which he impressed classmates with his promoting and selling techniques. Soon thereafter Benton was offered a Rhodes scholarship and had to confront the implications of his marketing aptitude. To his mother's dismay, he rejected it, instead accepting a prestigious summer training position in international trading and finance with National City Bank of New York.
That year brought major changes in his family situation as well. Elma Benton finished her degree work and was named headmistress at Hosmer Hall, a private girls' school in St. Louis, where she was to remain until her death in 1942. Dan Benton joined her there after spending the summer in New York City with his brother; but within a few months he had contracted an unidentified sleeping sickness, and he died in late December of 1919.
Benton had been elated to start his second year at Yale as one of the editors of the Yale Record, and soon after Dan's death he was elected chairman of the editorial board. Under his direction the staff solicited more advertising, and the magazine grew to boast the largest newsstand circulation of any college magazine in history. In addition to honing his writing and promotional skills, Benton formed important and long-lasting friendships during his college days. Among these men were Henry Luce, Jr., Robert M. Hutchins, Ralph Ingersoll, Galen Van Meter, and Reginald Marsh.
Graduating in 1921, Benton accepted a job with the National Cash Register Company, renowned for the quality of its salesmanship and the leadership of President John H. Patterson, the father of "scientific salesmanship." Within the earlier system, "drummers" had carried samples or catalogues demonstrating a range of products made by various manufacturers. Selling relied not only on the salesman's persuasiveness and personality but also on the customer's loyalty. The salesman had little incentive to improve performance since only novice or incompetent employees sold on commission; any good agent was tied to a set salary. Patterson revamped the system by assigning NCR salesmen specific territories, sales quotas, and a single product to be sold by creating a need for it among prospects. Another novel characteristic of Patterson's system was rewarding salesmen with generous prizes and more lucrative sales territories.
Benton's hiring violated two of Patterson's rules-of-thumb; he was under 25 and a college graduate. At first limited to menial or over-flow office work, Benton won an early chance to develop his selling skills because of his industriousness and aptitude. Despite being saddled with a notoriously unpromising trial territory, he exceeded his quota during his first month in the field. The auspicious beginning was insufficient inducement for company officials to waive minimum age requirements for NCR special training classes compulsory for advancement. Impatient and disenchanted, Benton decided to shift to advertising.
He broke into the new field with a $25-a-week job with the New York branch of Lord and Thomas, then the world's largest and most profitable advertising agency. Albert D. Lasker, its head and owner, brought to advertising the same dynamism and creativity that John H. Patterson infused into the world of scientific selling. Benton's dissatisfaction with the agency mounted rapidly, however, as his requests to learn copywriting were repeatedly denied. After a brief period of discontent he moved to the George Batten Company, staying there until fired as a result of policy disagreements a tumultuous five years later. Before returning to Lord and Thomas he married Helen Hemingway, a teacher he had met while at Yale. Their first child, Charles William, was born three years later. Several years later the Bentons adopted two baby girls, Louise Hemingway and Helen Orr, and in 1942 another child, John.
In 1929 Benton resigned as assistant general manager and partner at Lord and Thomas, and with former assistant Chester Bowles, from whom he borrowed $5,000 for the purpose, started the Benton and Bowles agency. Despite the Great Depression, Benton and Bowles quickly became the sixth largest single-office advertising firm in the United States. The Depression itself fostered the agency's success, for it encouraged the re-examination of advertising policies and outmoded techniques, facilitating the rise of a new wave of creative executives. The fledgling agency also benefited from Benton's introduction into New York of the consumer research surveys he had devised at Lord and Thomas in Chicago. These surveys gave clients more systematically compiled data for marketing decisions, particularly appealing at a time when consumer purchasing power was drastically reduced. In addition, while other top agencies still were depending almost totally on newspapers and national magazines, Benton and Bowles pioneered in radio advertising. Two shows were especially important;" Amos 'n Andy," which Benton bought for Pepsodent while still at Lord and Thomas; and the "Maxwell House Show Boat." Among the innovations on the latter were the use of the live studio audience, cue signs for laughter and applause, and commercials with sound effects.
The partners had agreed verbally from the outset that Benton would be free to leave with fair compensation when he chose, and in 1935 Benton began making arrangements to quit advertising. Newspapers seized the rags-to-riches story: Yale scholarship student reaches goal of earning a million dollars before his thirtieth birthday-and during the Depression. It is true that the eventual value of his stock made him a millionaire; but because his return was pegged to the firm's well-being, only if the agency continued to prosper would his total assets mount. Benton, in fact, was destined for some financially rocky periods before his wealth was assured.
When Benton announced his retirement from advertising, President Robert M. Hutchins, his former Yale debating partner, invited him to undertake public relations and fund-raising work for the University of Chicago. After Benton turned down the offer, Hutchins countered by proposing a shorter-term project; surveying University programs and suggesting improvements. As further inducement he stressed opportunities for directing and expanding the University's commitment to radio broadcasting and educational films, both areas which had already whetted Benton's interest.
Overcoming his initial hesitation, Benton agreed to spend two to three months assessing the situation and producing a "consumer research" survey for the institution. It was unprecedented for a university to adopt such techniques to measure its "acceptance" or "sales resistance." Indispensable assistance came from John Howe, then part of the University's public relations office and Benton's right-hand man for the ensuing three decades.
The University's public relations in the mid-thirties were in a poor state. Though it was outside the purview of his assignment, Benton managed to solve two of the institution's most vexing problems. The University was perceived as a nest of subversion, a situation which had been exacerbated by the publicity surrounding Charles Walgreen's withdrawal of his daughter from classes. Benton could uncover no factual basis for these accusations, so he got permission from Hutchins to approach the drugstore magnate personally. Their meeting laid the groundwork both for the resolution of the immediate problem and for Walgreen's underwriting of the University's Charles R. Walgreen Foundation for the Study of American Institutions. Benton was equally successful in neutralizing the chronic hostility shown the University by Chicago by newspapers, especially Colonel Robert McCormick's Chicago Tribune.
Late in 1936 Benton completed The University of Chicago's Public Relations, his analysis of the University's image problems and recommendations for improvement. Pinpointing Hutchins's role in public relations as crucial, he also underlined essential contributions to be made by faculty, students, trustees, and alumni. In line with his own interests and vision, he also emphasized the largely untapped capacity of radio and film to promote the University. Fifty confidential copies of the controversial report were printed for circulation to the trustees, and the University's public relations now so intrigued Benton that he agreed to assume a half-time position as vice-president.
He lost no time in implementing the ideas he had outlined in his report. In addition to producing and commissioning scores of promotional articles and pamphlets about the University, Benton lectured widely and urged others in the academic community to do the same. Much of this work was aimed at the Chicago business community, a group whose ties to the University the new vice president sought to strengthen and expand. Benton's greatest interest, however, was in radio and film. He put "The University of Chicago Round Table" on a permanent footing, arranging a grant from the Alfred Sloan Foundation for that purpose. Begun modestly in 1931 as an occasional seminar on current economic, political, and social issues, by the fall of 1936 the "Round Table" had a national following. Under Benton's tutelage it was for twenty years the most popular radio discussion program in the United States, drawing many of its participants from the University faculty. Benton further heightened the University's national visibility when he inaugurated another radio series, "The Human Adventure," which linked faculty research to dramatic advances in human knowledge.
Prospects for developing educational films were more complex. In 1932 the University had entered into a five-year contract with an AT&T subsidiary, Electrical Research Products, Inc. (ERPI), under which ERPI provided the financial and technical resources for film-making while the University supplied its faculty and endorsement. In 1936 Benton learned of the conglomerate's desire to sell ERPI and to abandon the educational film business. Despite the trustees' interest and Benton's strong encouragement, the University chose not to acquire ERPI. Benton's faith in the potential of the educational film business remained undiluted, and he was to have another chance to purchase ERPI only five years later.
During his years of service to the University, Benton continued to look for personal investment opportunities. In 1939 he bought Muzak, an ailing and obscure company which sent music into restaurants and hotels over leased telephone lines. The company's managers conceived of Muzak as a substitute for live orchestra and band music, but Benton revolutionized the business by envisioning it primarily as background music. Within a few years he had turned Muzak into a thriving concern, but he was stymied in his simultaneous efforts to introduce subscription radio, a scheme in which special FM channels would be made available to citizens on a subscription basis. By the late 1940s Benton was devoting his energies primarily to other concerns, though he retained ownership of the company until 1958.
Benton's association with the University led directly to another and even more profitable investment. Sears, Roebuck and Company had acquired Encyclopaedia Britannica after having been involved in its management during World War I, but the corporation was increasingly anxious to get rid of it. Benton knew General Robert E. Wood, chairman of Sears, from working closely with him on the America First Committee, and he suggested to Wood that Sears give the Britannica company to the University of Chicago as an endowment. The General agreed, but the University trustees balked at accepting the gift, worried about the lack of working capital and the appropriateness of a university's operating an essentially nonacademic book business. After months of negotiating, Hutchins, Benton, and Wood reached a compromise whereby Benton would supply $100,000 of working capital and assume risks of ownership and operation.
In early 1943 Benton thus became the owner, publisher, and chairman of the board of Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., and at the insistence of the University trustees he took two-thirds of the common stock. The University retained the option to buy one-half of his stock without interest, which would have given it two-thirds and control; when the time came to take up the option, the trustees were unwilling to tamper with a such a lucrative business arrangement. Benton eventually retired the University's holdings, but the institution continued to receive substantial royalty payments.
Shortly after assuming control of Britannica, Benton learned that ERPI was still available. To him it seemed natural for Encyclopaedia Britannica to acquire an educational film company, but it was a business gamble since all Benton's predecessors in that field had failed. The newborn Encyclopaedia Britannica Films, Inc., however, soon occupied an unexpectedly strong position in the field. Not only did its principal competitor, Eastman Kodak, withdraw from the business, but it donated its library of silent films to Encyclopaedia Britannica and the University of Chicago.
Another of Benton's projects grew out of his relationship with the University and Britannica. During his vice-presidential years, Benton became involved in Robert Hutchins's Great Books program, and in his enthusiasm he resolved to publish the works as a set. His Britannica associates were skeptical, reminding him of the ready availability of standard editions. Discounting their fears, he subsidized Mortimer Adler and an ever larger group of subeditors to compile the Syntopicon, a thesaurus of ideas within the Great Books of the Western World. Costs skyrocketed and deadlines were postponed again and again, but Benton's belief in the project never wavered. The 54-volume series finally appeared in 1952, its enormous commercial success vindicating Benton's judgment. In 1961 Britannica began publication of The Great Ideas Today, an annual supplement to the Great Books; two years later a companion set, the ten-volume Gateway to the Great Books, was published.
During his years at Chicago Benton also embarked on his career as a public servant. In 1939, as advisor to Nelson Rockefeller, then Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, he became engaged in the early U. S. ventures in international cultural exchanges. Three years later he was a founding member of the Committee for Economic Development, an organization of top businessmen devoted to planning postwar employment and production. In 1945 Benton severed his administrative connection with the University of Chicago to become Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs. His responsibilities included consolidating the wartime information agencies within the State Department and launching the first major U. S. programs for peacetime international information and educational exchanges. Benton was ideally suited to these tasks, but he knew that success would depend on his ability to educate Congress and the American public.
Under his direction the State Department began the Voice of America broadcasts, established the United States information offices, and promoted international visits of professors and students. Benton also led U. S. participation in organizing UNESCO, which he later served as representative under the Kennedy and Johnson administrations. He was busy on the legislative front as well, guiding through Congress the Foreign Service Act of 1946 and the Fulbright Act for international educational exchange programs.
Benton resigned from the State Department in 1947 and planned to give his attention to Britannica affairs. Soon thereafter, however, because of his international experience and his years of work with the Commission on the Freedom of the Press, the State Department asked him to lead the American delegation to the 1948 United Nations Conference on Freedom of Press and Information. Until his death twenty-five years later Benton continued his work with American delegations to numerous international conferences.
Late in 1949 a new path of service opened up to Benton when his old business partner, Chester Bowles, then governor of Connecticut, appointed him to fill a vacant U. S. Senate seat. The next year Benton ran to win the two years remaining in the term. His energetic and creative promotional skills once again found an appropriate arena; he introduced the helicopter into political campaigning and used radio and television extensively. The new techniques were effective; Benton was elected, while Bowles and the rest of the state ticket were defeated.
In the Senate Benton joined other liberal Democrats in supporting Truman's Fair Deal. He became a member of the Banking and Currency Committee, the Rules Committee, the Select Committee on Small Business, and the Joint Committee on the Economic Report. Benton introduced and saw enacted a Mutual Security Act amendment stipulating that the act's administrators when purchasing foreign-made materials give preference to factories with noncommunist leadership. He was especially disappointed to have failed with his "Marshall Plan of Ideas," a six-part program designed to combat communism and promote freedom of information.
Benton's voting record supported civil rights and other liberal policies, with a single exception which was to be a lasting source of regret to him. He had been steadfast in his opposition to the Internal Security Act (also known as the McCarran Immigration Act) on the grounds that it was pointedly restrictive of eastern and southern Europeans. Political considerations within the Senate convinced him to swallow his objections and to cast his vote with the overwhelming majority in its favor. It was vetoed immediately by Truman, only to be overridden by Congress. In early 1952 Benton returned to his original stance, joining Senators Lehman and Humphrey in opposing a more extreme version; however, this bill too was enacted over presidential veto. Benton continued to work on immigration after leaving the Senate, primarily by helping organize and finance the National Committee on Immigration and Citizenship. The committee's efforts were rewarded by the 1965 adoption of an immigration policy it deemed liberal and humane.